Guide to the Cathy Davidson Papers, 1969-2010s RL.10162
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Cathy Davidson papers
1969-2010s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.10162
13.5 Linear Feet
Former English Professor at Duke University, and Vice-Provost for Interdisciplinary Affairs. Author of fiction and memoirs, and editor of The Book of Love and Oxford Companion to Women's Writing in the United States. The Cathy Davidson Papers encompass Davidson's various writings, organizational work, correspondence, and materials related to Fred Hampton.
Access Restrictions
Permission from Cathy Davidson is required to view any materials in accession 2012-0488 (boxes 21-23) during her lifetime.
Provenance
The Cathy Davidson Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1996-2017.
Biographical Note
Cathy Davidson (1949- ) is a scholar, university professor, and author/editor of eighteen books. She received her B.A. from Elmhurst College and her M.A. and Ph.D. from Binghamton University. Davidson has served as the Ruth F. DeVarney Professor of English at Duke University since 1996 and has held a second distinguished chair as the John Hope Franklin Humanities Institute Professor of Interdisciplinary Studies since 2006. Her leadership positions span various organizations, including the American Studies Association and the American Literature Association. Davidson's works explore her interest in the relationship between social and political activities and the creative arts, particularly fiction.
Collection Overview
The Cathy Davidson Papers encompass Davidson's various writings, organizational work, correspondence, and materials related to Fred Hampton. The Writings Series includes her research and assemblage of famous authors' love letters (Book of Love), as well as drafts of various books, short stories, writing workshops, and publication matters. The Organizations and Professional Activities Series includes files relating to her work with the American Studies Association, the American Literature Section of the MLA, and the American Literature Association, as well as various other professional activities. Part of Davidson's Duke career is documented in the papers as well, particularly her work with the MacArthur Foundation grant for learning institutions in a digital age, as well as some HASTAC materials. The Fred Hampton Materials pertain to the assassination of Fred Hampton in 1969 and Davidson's related photography projects. This series is closed until 2017. Additionaly, permission from Cathy Davidson is required to view any materials in accession 2012-0248 (boxes 21-23) during her lifetime.
Conditions Governing Access
Some materials in this collection fall under University Archives restrictions and are closed for 25 years from their date of creation.
Conditions Governing Access
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Contact Research Services to request the production of listening/viewing copies.
Women authors; Audiocassettes; American literature -- History and criticism; Authors, American; Davidson, Cathy N., 1949-; American Studies Association
- Writings, 1990s-2010s, 12 boxes
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Permission from Cathy Davidson is required to view any materials in accession 2012-0248 (boxes 21-23) during her lifetime.
  Scope and Contents note
  Within the Writings Series are notes, drafts and correspondence relating to Davidson's published and unpublished written works. These include Davidson's research and assemblage of famous authors' love letters that make up the Book of Love: Writers and Their Love Letters Subseries. In Boxes 1-2, files are arranged alphabetically by writer and include permissions and other copyright information. Also included are subseries on Davidson's published books: Now You See It: How the Brain Science of Attention will Transform the Way we Live, Work, and Learn; Thirty-Six Views of Mount Fuji: On Finding Myself in Japan; and Revolution and the Word: the Rise of the Novel in America. The Assorted Writings Subseries includes notes, research, and drafts of various books, short stories, writing workshops, and publication materials.
  - Book of Love: Writers and Their Love Letters
    - Abelard/Heloise-Hemingway (Box 1)
    - Miller-Wollstonecraft (Box 2)
    - Questionnaires, permissions, correspondence (Box 3-4)
    - Love Letters / OUP (Box 21)
    - Love letters for grandma / WRB (Box 21)
    - Royalties (Box 21)
    - Contract (Box 21)
    - Reviews (Box 21)
    - PR (Box 21)
    - Correspondence: Falk, Katherine (Box 21)
    - Correspondence: Rosenman, Jane, 2 folders (Box 21)
    - Love letters (Box 21)
    - Permissions (Box 21)
    - Agent files, proposal, drafts, and permissions (Box 26)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes files from literary agent H. Merrill.
    - Scrapbook and praise for The Book of Love, 1992-1993; 2 folders (Box 35)
    - Jean Feraca: Writers and their Love Letters. Interview with Cathy Davidson, WPR, University of Wisconsin, 1993 June 17 (Box 33, Audio-cassette RL10162-CS-0005)
    - The Book of Love: National Humanities Center, RTP, NC. Side A, 1992 (Box 33, Audio-cassette RL10162-CS-0006)
    - A Book of Love on WBEZ, 1993 Feb. 12 (Box 33, Audio-cassette RL10162-CS-0012)
  - Now You See It: How the Brain Science of Attention will Transform the Way we Live, Work, and Learn
    - Notes (Box 21)
      Includes 1 audiocassette tape.
    - Lectures (Box 21)
      Includes 2 audiocassette tapes.
    - Release forms (Box 21)
    - Our national learning disorder (Box 21)
    - I saw the figure 5 in gold (Box 21)
  - Thirty-Six Views of Mount Fuji: On Finding Myself in Japan
    - Correspondence (Box 21)
      - General correspondence, 2folders (Box 21)
      - Thoma, Geri, 3 folders (Box 21)
      - Klayman, Rachel (Box 21)
    - Soundings (Box 21)
    - Letters (Box 21)
    - Life (Box 21)
    - Flap copy (Box 21)
    - Paperback (Box 21)
    - Questionnaire (Box 21)
    - Japanese translator DHC (Box 21)
    - 2005 Release (Box 21)
    - Copy editing and serials (Box 21)
    - Glossary (Box 21)
    - Catalogue copy (Box 21)
    - Serials (Box 21)
    - Ontario review (Box 21)
    - Cover and pages (Box 21)
    - PR (Box 21)
    - Japan book / OUP (Box 21)
    - Black-and-white art from the book, undated (Box 35)
    - Scrapbook / praise, 1993 (Box 35)
    - "36 Views of Mt Fuji" 29:45, PSA's at :40, 16:38, 26:00, Pankhurst Communications, NYC, undated (Box 33, Audio-cassette RL10162-CS-0008)
    - 36 Views of Mt. Fuji, National Humanities Center, RTP, NC. Side A, 1993 (Box 33, Audio-cassette RL10162-CS-0011)
  - Revolution and the Word: the Rise of the Novel in America
    - Oxford: EAL book (Box 21)
    - Oxford contract (Box 21)
    - Oxford revision and style sheet (Box 21)
    - Panel Discussion (Box 21)
    - Reviews (Box 21)
    - Copy editing (Box 21)
    - Notes (Box 21)
    - Draft (expanded edition), 2003 (Box 34)
  - Assorted Writings
    - Assorted Writings (Box 3-10)
    - Rough Cut
      - Notes (Box 21)
      - Paris 7/5/03 - 7/20/03 (Box 21)
      - Chapter summary (Box 21)
      - Character questionnaire (Box 21)
      - Plot outline Chapters 1-6 (Box 21)
    - Humanities manifesto (Box 22)
    - Intellectual diversity (Box 22)
    - Michael Moon intro (Box 22)
    - Umea talk (Box 22)
    - Vitae (Box 22)
    - Gender
      - Gender articles (Box 22)
      - Pleasure bibliography sexuality essay (Box 22)
      - Resources/databases (Box 22)
      - Kerber - Common Place 2002 (Box 22)
      - Lewis - Common Place 2002 (Box 22)
    - Chronicle of Higher Education forum (Box 22)
    - ACLS (Box 22)
    - Duke Magazine (Box 22)
    - NEH (Box 22)
    - Academe (Box 22)
    - ADE 2009 (Box 22, Box 34)
    - Misc. writing (Box 22)
    - Oxford Handbook for Interdisciplinarity (Box 22)
    - Technology (Box 22)
    - Captivity: review essay (Box 22)
    - Constitution (Box 22)
    - Death penalty (Box 22)
    - Declaration of Independence (Box 22)
    - Intellectual property / copyright (Box 22)
    - Market revolution (Box 22)
    - New Historicism (Box 22)
    - Engaging Humanities (Box 22, Box 34)
    - Ideology and genre (Box 22)
    - Nepantla essay (Box 22)
    - Common Place, 3 folders (Box 22)
    - Bogliasco (Box 22)
    - Digital Youth - Tokyo (Box 22)
    - Tammy Rae Carland (Box 22)
    - Future of Institutions (Box 22)
    - Equiano
      - Emancipation Timeline (Box 22)
      - Correspondence (Box 22)
    - AI, Animals, Alife (Box 22)
    - Interdisciplinarity (Box 22)
    - Indexicality (Box 22)
    - Iowa Course Materials (Box 22)
    - Newsday taxes and offshore (Box 22)
    - Penguin Zelimir Contract (Box 22)
    - Cindy Sherman (Box 22)
    - Duke University Press article (Box 22)
    - PMLA essay (Box 22)
    - Digitizing humanities (Box 22)
    - Photographs of the Dead
      - Rowson, Charlotte Temple photographs of graves (Box 22)
      - Solomon - Godeau, Abigail (Box 22)
      - SAQ (Box 22)
      - NIU Iowa 3/97 (Box 22)
      - MSU (Box 22)
    - Drafts of published and unpublished books, stories, etc. (Box 27-28)
      Works include The Last Weekend, Stet, Flashback, Odd One Out, Rough Cut, and Air Kisses, along with other drafts and excerpts. Boxes also include agent correspondence, research files, and supplemental materials.
    - Oxford Companion to Women's Writing in the United States (Box 31-32, Box 35)
      Files include author entries, indices, drafts, proposals, and other materials from Davidson's work as editor of the Oxford Companion. Also includes a scrapbook (disbound) with reviews, fan letters, and press coverage.
    - Scrapbook and fan mail for various works, 1994 and undated (Box 35)
    - What's the Word? #2. Literature Matters, MLA, undated (Box 33, Audio-cassette RL10162-CS-0007)
    - "The Conversation" WCHL 1360 AM, 1994 Feb. 17 (Box 33, Audio-cassette RL10162-CS-0009)
    - Closing Davidson, 1998 May 5 (Box 33, Audio-cassette RL10162-CS-0010)
- Organizations and Professional Activities, 1987-2010s, 9 boxes
  The Organizations Series documents Davidson's work with the American Studies Association, including items related to ASA history, articles, conferences, and Davidson's committee participation, as well as her work with the American Literature Section of the MLA, particularly her editorial work with American Literature. Her work with the American Literature Association and various other professional activities are also represented in this series.
  - American Studies Association
    Materials related to Davidson's work with the American Studies Association.
    - American Studies Association (Box 10-15)
    - American Studies Association: American Quarterly Board workings (Box 19)
    - ASA 1997 Conference (Box 19)
    - ASA 1999 Conference (Box 19)
    - ASA 2000 Conference (Box 19)
    - ASA 2002 panel (Box 22)
    - ASA - NEH Sheldon Hackney response (Box 22)
    - Conferences, committees, 2001-2005 (Box 34)
  - Modern Language Association: American Literature Section
    Materials related to Davidson's work with the American Literature Section of the MLA and American Literature.
    - Correspondence (Box 19)
    - American Literature Expanded Board (Box 19)
    - American Literature business: budget and expenses (Box 19)
    - American Literature business: computers (Box 19)
    - American Literature business: logging procedures (Box 19)
    - American Literature business: production schedule (Box 19)
    - American Literature business: quarterly report (Box 19)
    - American Literature business: Erich Staib (Box 19)
    - American Literature business: subscription (Box 19)
    - American Literature business: student subscription list (Box 19)
    - American Literature business: Carol Rigsby salary (Box 19)
    - American Literature business: Carol Rigsby promotion materials (Box 19)
    - American Literature business: acting editor (Box 19)
    - American Literature editorial: American Quarterly Board workings (Box 19)
    - American Literature editorial: brief mentions (Box 19)
    - American Literature editorial: Anne Durden (Box 19)
    - American Literature editorial: editorial assistant (Box 19)
    - American Literature editorial: editorial schedule (Box 19)
    - American Literature editorial: extras (Box 19)
    - American Literature editorial: general correspondence (Box 19)
    - American Literature editorial: intern (Box 19)
    - American Literature editorial: American Literary History and other competitors (Box 19)
    - American Literature editorial: Guide Lines to the Editing and Publishing of American Literature (Box 19)
    - American Literature archives (Box 19)
    - No More Separate Spheres (Box 19)
    - American Literature Board (Box 19)
    - Strandberg/Houston Baker (Box 19)
    - Visiting Editor requests (Box 19)
    - Adams essay/Ferraro (Box 20)
    - MLA/ALS (Box 20)
    - American Literature correspondence and reports (Box 20)
    - Editorship of American Literature, late 1960s-early 1970s (Box 20)
    - Editorship of American Literature, 1980s (Box 20)
      Also includes information on the rewriting of the Articles of Agreement between Duke University and the American Literature Section.
    - Current affairs of the American Literature Section (Box 20)
    - American Literature Section (Box 20)
    - MLA 1989 (Box 22)
    - MLA 1991 (Box 22)
    - MLA 1994 (Box 22)
    - MLA Paper on games 2006 (Box 22)
  - American Literature Association (Box 15)
  - Grant proposal: Australia Fulbright (Box 20)
  - Vietnam (Box 20)
  - National Public Radio (Box 20)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 20)
  - Old business (Box 20)
  - Aesthetics and Difference conference (Box 20)
  - University of California Humanities Research Institute, 2001-2002 (Box 34)
    Correspondence with David Goldberg, logistics, and reports.
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 2004-2006 (Box 34)
    Correspondence/writings by Donald Summers
  - American Council of Learned Societies, 2002-2006 (Box 34)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 2003-2009; 5 folders (Box 34)
    Includes proposals and correspondence on various initiatives, some connected with Davidson's role at Duke and some independent NEH programs
  - Modern Language Association, 2001-2008; 3 folders (Box 34)
  - CHAT: Digital Arts and Humanities festival, 2010 (Box 34)
  - Full Frame Festival: Creativity and the University "Big Ideas" symposium, 2006 (Box 34)
  - Columbia University: Center for Comparative Literature and Society report, 2005; 2 folders (Box 34)
  - Association of American Universities: Interdisciplinary Task Force, 2005 (Box 34)
  - Artistic License, undated (Box 33, Audio-cassette RL10162-CS-0013)
  - Cathy Davidson- CSPAN superstar, undated (Box 33, Video-cassette RL10162-VHS-0001)
  - Split screens / split subjects, undated (Box 33, Video-cassette RL10162-VHS-0002)
  - Cathy Davidson on Charlie Rose, 1992 Dec. 9 (Box 33, Video-cassette RL10162-VHS-0003)
- Duke materials
  Subject and research files relating to Davidson's role in a MacArthur foundation grant for Future of Learning Institutions in a Digital Age at Duke University. Also includes some miscellaneous materials from the Franklin Humanities Institute, HASTAC, and Interdisciplinary Studies.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Portions of this series (box 36) fall under University Archives restrictions and are closed for 25 years from their date of creation.
  - HASTAC programs and brochures (Box 17)
  - HASTAC conference (Box 22)
  - Research files on information in the digital age, A-Z (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous files on MOOCs, college education, and other topics (Box 24)
  - MacArthur Foundation materials
    - MacArthur Foundation grant materials, Future of Learning Institutions in a Digital Age, 2006-2007 (Box 18)
    - Digital media and learning, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Civic engagement (Box 23)
    - Civic engagement online (Box 23)
    - Digital institutions (Box 23)
    - Learning in the information age (Box 23)
    - Future of learning institutions - Irvine notes (Box 23)
    - Notes for Expanding cyber-communities PowerPoint (Box 23)
    - Digital Learning (Durham) (Box 23)
    - Article on Gordon Bell (Box 23)
    - Social software (Box 23)
    - Grand Theft Auto (Box 23)
    - Shock of the old technology and global history (Box 23)
    - MacArthur competition (Box 23)
    - Future of learning institutions in a digital age (Box 23)
    - Technology is not enough lecture (Box 23)
  - Commencement program from Davidson's honorary doctorate from Northwestern University, 2005 (Box 18)
  - "Social Disaster" advertisement, African and African American Studies, 2006 (Box 18)
  - "Promoting Interdisciplinarity" article by Davidson, 2005 (Box 18)
  - Franklin Humanities Institute publicity (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous materials from Duke (Box 18)
  - Junana, by Bruce Caron (Box 18)
  - Course notes
    - 381, 4 folders (Box 22)
    - 169, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Grade book (Box 22)
    - F96 Graduate course (Box 22)
    - "This is your brain on the internet" course, 2010 (Box 34)
  - Faculty Annual Report (Box 22)
  - Trinity Board of Visitors (Box 22)
  - Faculty Newsletter (Box 22)
  - Miscellaneous English course files (Box 24)
  - Literary subject files, A-Z (Box 25-26)
    Davidson's research files on authors, subjects, and literary works used in her teaching of literature courses.
  - Emory Elliott visit to Franklin Humanities Institute, 2003 (Box 34)
  - Duke-DiTella Workshop logistics, research, 2001-2002 (Box 34)
  - Digital Media and Learning Competition (HASTAC/MacArthur Foundation), 2008-2009 (Box 34)
  - Storming the Academy notes, undated (Box 34)
  - Travel itineraries, reimbursements, logistics, 2007-2010 (Box 34)
  - Interface: JHF Institute seminar, 2006 (Box 34)
  - Sanford Institute meeting notes, emails, 2005 (Box 36)
    Materials fall under University Archives restrictions and are closed for 25 years from the date of creation.
  - Sanford Task Force Report, with Davidson's notes, 2005 Aug. (Box 36)
  - Duke Central Campus Planning Committee, 2005-2006 (Box 36)
  - Digital Futures Task Force, 2009 (Box 36)
  - University courses: planning, policies, 2004-2006 (Box 36)
- Correspondence, 1 box
  Includes both personal and professional correspondence.
  - Correspondence - Personal (Box 23)
  - Curtis Taylor (Box 23)
  - Friends' letters 1995 (Box 23)
  - Diego Cortez (Box 23)
  - Nancy Ainsworth (Box 23)
  - Amsterdam (Box 23)
  - Guggenheim Fellowship (Box 23)
  - Awards (Box 23)
  - Bellagio Study and Conference Center (Box 23)
  - Hopkins (Box 23)
  - Susan Koppelman (Box 23)
  - Broner (Box 23)
  - Clips - Ms, Vogue (Box 23)
  - Duke U Press (Box 23)
  - Linda Gottlieb (Box 23)
  - Misc. (Box 23)
  - Ms. (Box 23)
  - Michigan State / NYU lecture (Box 23)
  - Michigan State University (Box 23)
  - NEA (Box 23)
  - NYE (Box 23)
  - Book reviews (Box 23)
  - Lora Romero (Box 23)
  - Sabbatical (Box 23)
  - Alix Shullman (Box 23)
  - Dale Spender (Box 23)
  - Anna Deavere Smith (Box 23)
  - Sugimoto (Box 23)
  - Ted Davidson (Box 23)
  - Joyce Oates (Box 23)
  - Sedgwick (Box 23)
  - USIA (Box 23)
  - USIS (Box 23)
  - Virginia (Box 23)
  - Vogue (Box 23)
  - American Literature, 2 folders (Box 23)
  - Oxford University Press - New projects (Box 23)
  - Oxford publicity department (Box 23)
  - Australia - ANZASA (Box 23)
  - Computers (Box 23)
  - WSQ (Box 23)
  - Correspondence, 1994-2007; 7 folders (Box 34)
    Personal correspondence and fan mail for a variety of works, including 36 Views of Mt. Fuji.
  - Arac, Jonathon, 2004 (Box 34)
  - Address book (photocopy), undated (Box 34)
  - Perkins, David: News and Observer, 1994-1995 (Box 34)
- General Subject Files, A-Z
  - Subject files (Box 29-30)
- Fred Hampton Materials, 1969-1995, 1 box
  The Fred Hampton Series pertains to Fred Hampton, an African-American activist and chairman of the Illinois chapter of the Black Panther Party, who was killed in 1969. Materials include Chicago Tribune clippings and various photographs and correspondence.
  - Fred Hampton Materials (Box 16)